uh okay so why don't we uh get this part
is party started
uh so joining us today um
we've got brendan monroe and eaton lamb
from
icici bank canada now i gotta be honest
every time i see i see ici bank i want
to keep going and i just want to say i
see i see i see i see ici
but that's just me i'm sure i'm the only
one that's ever done that
so anyway over to you brendan and eden
uh
feel free to take it over uh we're gonna
have you as the
opening yes you guys can kind of have i
always like kind of say about half an
hour
uh and then then you can bail out and
we'll just carry on with the rest of our
meeting
i can promise you it's not gonna be a
half hour where you have a nice tidy
little discussion for us and if you want
to send us
you know lots of particular file
questions at the end then happy to do
that as well but uh
awesome and we're a pretty talkative
group too so
i encourage everyone to have the
questions i'll moderate and i'll watch
the chat
side of things but uh we'll we'll feel
free to we like to interrupt so just so
you know
great thanks for the warning um good
afternoon everyone i'm brendan monroe
i'm the bdm for
icici cici bank
it stands for the industrial credit and
investment corporation of india bank
which
was founded back in the mid 20th century
and since that time icici has grown to
be an international financial powerhouse
one of the largest private banks
headquartered in india
with operations nearly 20 countries
around the world despite the
enormity of icici on a global scale
we're definitely a niche
lender in the mortgage space in british
columbia in canada
and we'll talk about some of the niche
solutions that we've carved out for
ourselves
in british columbia in the last few
years you'll find that all of our
mortgage servicing our mortgage
underwriting and mortgage sales are all
done here in canada so you're not
calling the indian call
center or uh for assistance um you're
either speaking with me you're speaking
with somebody
uh my underwriting team they're all here
in in canada in
places like edmonton or toronto and i'm
of course
located in uh east vancouver i'd love to
get out to
see you all in the okanagan as soon as
we get uh coveted lifted in the meantime
we have
zoo meetings like this which make me uh
wish i could get onto
you know road trips have some wine with
you but in the meantime this is the best
we're going to do um
pete would you mind if i share a screen
i got a standard slide deck
let's see if i can do this without
requiring permission host has disabled
participant screen sharing
yeah flip switch that we can uh get that
i think you should be able to see that
you're now a co-host
great yeah
powerpoints
awesome so icici bank has two main lines
of business
we do a insured business and we do a
conventional business
you'll see some other lenders have
another bucket that is the insurable
or their back-end bulk insured icici
doesn't do that we're just strictly
insured files or conventional files
there's many great lenders on the
insured space across british columbia
it's
really you know a commodity you want to
have great service and great
relationships there on that insurance
side and there's also going to be
a huge differentiator on price
everybody's competing for the lowest
price
i think you can find that icici bank is
very very competitive on the pricing
side
on insured mortgages with rates as low
as 1.69 on fixed right now
uh variable rates starting at prime
minus one percent so you can definitely
be in the conversation in the mix with
icici as far as insured product
and all the regular lender guidelines
apply for insured like
gds tds of 3944 amortizations of 25
years
you've seen all those constraints before
we just basically align with all those
insurer guidelines
a couple things we do that are a bit
unique uninsured is if you have
non-subject rentals
you're deriving some income from but
you're buying uh you know
subject-insured property
we have a very nice worksheet that
you'll usually be allowed to use for
that non-subject income
we also automatically float down the
rates for your clients between
commitment and funding
so you don't have to call your
underwriter and ask for an exception
because the market rates went down so if
you've got a file committed with us and
we go down another five or ten basis
points
that benefit will automatically flow
through to the borrower
we use the child canada tax benefit up
to 100
in most cases so that can make the
difference for those families that are
trying to
get onto the property ladder and using
some of that income or we can use
100 of it most of the time when it comes
to our conventional business we do a lot
in the purchase we do a lot in the
refinance we do a lot in the
rental property business as well
we do up to an 80 loan to value and up
to 1.5 million dollars
and we don't apply a sliding scale so
that's going to be different than what
you see from other lenders where once
you're over that
million dollar mark they're starting to
adjust things we're just going to lend
money at the regular rates rate up to 80
loan to value right at our regular
conventional rates
brandon is that across canada is or is
that particular to bc
we're talking about bc we're talking
about ontario
if you have a deal that's in the
prairies just give me a call
everything's
weird and different in the prairies
based on how things are set up right now
and so we'll take those files on like a
case-by-case basis but i'll give you the
uh
the bc and ontario situations because
they're the most common and that's
straight across bc it's like uh not in
uh the major centers or what
i can get into a coverage map because i
think that's going to be you know
important for
your team here in uh in the okanagan
because some of the communities we
are really happy to lend into and other
ones are a little bit trickier for us so
maybe i'll just create a bit of a space
in the conversation here for that in
just a couple minutes
gds tds ratios we have a very high
tolerance for elevated gds tds on
conventional
so 4247 gds tds we'll do all day
and then if you have a client who is a
little bit higher than that we have an
extended ratios program
there's a couple of provisos or
qualifiers for that program but that can
extend ratios all the way up to
50 55 and so that's a unique way that we
handle some of those uh
elevated ratios and i'll talk about that
more in a moment
um before i get into credit maybe i'll
just talk about lending areas i don't
think i have a slide specifically but i
know that's come up a couple of times in
conversations with
with brokers here from your office if
it's an insured file
and it's pretty much anywhere in the
okanagan area
um the insurers are happy with it we're
probably going to be happy with it too
so insured files we have that backup
from the insurer and
if places like you know penticton or
soyuz or smaller centers
we're probably going to be able to
confidently do an insured file there
if it's an owner occupied conventional
file
we want to look at the communities that
are 10 000 plus
or that are within a 75 kilometer
distance of downtown from one of those
communities
so we're happy to go to vernon we're
happy to go to kelowna we're happy to go
to west
kelowna um we're happy to go to places
like salmon arm because they're within
that 75
kilometer distance from one of those
centers if you're looking at
you know a place like lake country um
talk to me if it's owner occupied it
should be okay
but we're really treating some of those
smaller communities on a case-by-case
basis we're not quite at the credit
union level where we'll
you know just lend everywhere in small
town but we're going to try to make it
work as best we can for you
out in the in the okanagan especially on
owner occupied
lake country is like 10k outside of
kelowna
i know i know i don't know i've had a
couple of inquiries from your team
already that before and it was for
rentals and we said no because they're a
rental refinance or rental purchase
and we're a lot more constrained on
rentals for what we do we basically want
to be right in town
in in kelowna um or even you know raiden
town
maybe vernon but we're looking at just
how how many sales how many transactions
are taking place in that community year
to year
we want really a lot of volume a lot of
liquidity before we're able to
you know do a loan on a investment condo
or an investment house
in the okanagan so primarily we're
looking at owner occupied
for purchases and refinances if you have
an investment property it's in the
okanagan it's in kelowna
great if it's somewhere outside of
kelowna let's just talk about it
specifically and we'll see if we can
make it work
brendan we're good in penticton yeah
yeah penticton has what 15 20 000 people
there
about 34 000. it's grown that's great
yeah then we'll do owner occupied in a
place like that and then uh
your your rental side might be a little
bit trickier
but if it's owner occupier the basement
that's still fine when i say when i say
rental i just mean like a purely
investment property
let's talk about credit um on the
conventional side of icici's business
um let's start with high ratio we want
you know
we're looking for the aaa type borrowers
with 700 plus credit
um even down to 680 is probably okay as
long as we can sell it on the insurer
and they're usually
sort of pushing back on files that are
below 680 uninsured right now
but on the conventional side we have a
lot more flexibility
so we have policies that are somewhere
between the a space and the b
space is probably the best way of
looking at it we're not looking for the
pure b deal and we're probably not going
to compete
very aggressively with the the scosas
and the tds on the really pure a deal
either
we're looking for those clients that
fall in between a and b you might want
to call it b
plus uh you might call it a minus i know
i'd be a lot more comfortable with a
minus on my report card but if that
sounds like your client
and uh the big bank said no then before
you send
a file over to an equitable or a haven
tree or
optimum or a home trust or whoever your
favorite b lender is
pick up the phone give me a call send me
an email see if that fits
before you send it off to one of those
pure b lenders
we're happy to work with borrowers whose
credit starts with a
beacon starts with a six so if you have
a primary applicant who's
the one who's making the more income on
the file that's your primary applicant
and if their beacon score starts with a
six then
we're pretty much on side um if there
are secondary beacons a little bit lower
than that then
you know again case by case uh we're not
looking for like i said really b
deals where both applicants are uh in
the 500s but if you're in somewhere in
the 600 range then we certainly want to
consider that file
if you have no beacon especially if it's
like a nudity canada scenario we could
probably find a solution for that
sometimes no credit is better than bad
credit and we have some some policies
that we can
work through those low credits or no
credit situations
brendan uh do you look at equifax or
transunion as well
we look at equifax primarily we can look
at transunion usually we'll do like a
average of the two and if something
shows i've seen sometimes where equifax
is like
not great but transient is a lot
stronger so we want to do an average of
those two bureaus in that situation
when we're talking about conventional
mortgages we can do up to 80
loan to value on most property types so
that's purchases refinances
rentals we allow a 30-year amortization
we talked about the 4247
gds tds ratios we don't change our
rates if they go above that number we
don't change their rates if they're in
the upper range of that number we just
have our regular conventional rates that
apply
uh we do have an extended ratios program
that can help get those rates
or those ratios up to 50 55. and in
order to qualify for that program we're
gonna have one of the applicants that's
earning eighty thousand dollars a year
of employment income so they're a nice
solid salary borrower with predictable
income
and we're able to risk mitigate with a
one percent lender setup fee at the
point of funding so that uh that program
helps us for
couples that maybe are going through a
separation and one of the people wants
to keep the matrimonial home
that can be a really great solution with
those high elevated gds tds
it's also really helpful in those
scenarios where you have somebody who
went out and
you know they bought a land rover and
then walk into your office a few weeks
later saying i got that
new car in the driveway now help me get
a mortgage everything's going well at
work uh
you know promotion and now i got all
this money and i'm spending it so
obviously you know that the order in
which they purchase things has a bearing
on this but if you have a
borrower who did things slightly out of
order that elevated
tds gds might be able to help save that
file
you said you interrupt lots pete so if
you have any questions you know
this is probably good why are they
buying land rovers come on
that is the question isn't it why would
you
look nice in your driveway of your
rental property where you're paying the
rent
uh when it comes to rental properties we
have a very unique rental income
treatment
if you have an owner-occupied property
that is the subject
and uh you have a basement suite or a
laneway house in that property
we can apply an 80 rental offset in most
cases
which means your gds tds ratios are
automatically going to go down very
aggressively because we're offsetting
most of that pni with the rental income
so it's a great tool for you who
have clients that have a basement suite
might be able to get that done here with
icici we won't be able to get that done
elsewhere
also when it comes to renter occupied
investment properties that are the
subject
so that's you know the pure rental
properties
we're going to apply an 80 offset on
most property types we're going to apply
a 50
offset on condos we're also going to
allow you to exclude the taxes and heat
from the ratio calculation
so again some very unique treatments of
the the rental income
to help your clients they're looking to
become semi-professional landlords known
you know one two three four even more
investment properties
all of our investment property files
attract a one percent letter setup fee
so just good to know about that up front
and uh
for renter occupied investment
properties that are non-subject so let's
say they already own
five or six rental properties and
they're looking to refinance them
one of them they're looking to refinance
multiple they're looking to maybe add
another
house to that portfolio and we use a
very
uh easy to use and very beneficial
worksheet that
does not limit the number of doors so
the rental worksheet is going to capture
the qualifying income for your four
favorite properties in the portfolio
and then properties number five six
seven eight um there's a column
to be able to capture that income and
just exclude the income and just debt
service those properties i'll show you
what i mean on the next slide
there's no number there's no maximum
number of doors and then when you're
done your work on the
rental worksheet you're going to add the
surplus back to gross income
i'll show you what i mean by that yes
please
and if you have one of these uh excel
sheets on your desk and you're
curious about how it works i'm happy to
walk you through it it's available in
our portal
you guys have access to our mortgage
broker portal um
and if not i'll make sure you do but our
rental worksheet allows us in these
first four columns property one property
two property three property four
that's where you're going to put in all
the pertinent details on a rental
property that they own
and in the fifth property which is
mostly fifth column which is mostly
blacked out
there's a cell for monthly principal
interest
so you'll see that we're not using the
income from property number five or six
or seven
so you might have a really strong number
from the first four columns you might
have a
negative number from that that last
column because we're just applying the
pni and not the
income from it so what that means is
we're going to treat all these
properties as profit centers and
not necessarily as liabilities so if you
have a borrower that has 567 properties
this might come out as a wash it might
come out as a zero that you're adding to
gross income but you're also not worried
about all those extra properties being
liabilities
so keep this in mind if you have those
semi-professional investors
who have a wide number of properties in
their portfolio
in a lot of cases we can actually just
use that income and add it to gross
which is helpful and if they have you
know a number of properties beyond
number four then
we're not going to give them a really
tough treatment on that liability side
that make sense so far i'll plug it in
and figure out how it looks because i've
got a file
that sounds great give me a call if the
uh if
it doesn't make sense but this you'll
find it's very easy to use once you're
in there
and it usually produces a nice green
number at the bottom that you can add to
uh to gross income
which is helpful yeah i've used this
before with other clients
but i was perplexed by this description
so i'll give it a run
okay thank you wonderful
uh we also like to position ourselves as
a lender that's between the a and the b
space on conventional
so i mentioned if you get a decline for
one of the big banks before you send it
off to the pure b lender you know give
us a call
we can probably help you out with your
hourly or part-time employees
that might not fit the bank's uh terms
and conditions
we have a program for bfs clients that
have been in the business for a little
under 24 months
whereas other lenders probably want two
years we can certainly work with beacons
that are in the lower range of the 600s
and we also do private mortgage payouts
so we can be a very excellent
exit strategy for those borrowers who
got into a private mortgage a year or
two ago and have sort of
got things figured out they need a
little more runway before they get into
a
so send that file to us as part of an
exit strategy to get out of one of those
private mortgages
we'll refinance the property and get
them into
a reasonable rate of interest that helps
them
re-establish themselves over usually a
three p three year period i found its
most common one and uh that'll help them
on their journey from b to a
so on your hourly if i get back brendan
they're
on the income side for uh hourly
part-time employees etc
would that could that be used uh
possibly for a
high ratio application
i mean it's one of those things yeah
where the employment letter you know
shows up that they're supposed to be
getting paid for 38 to 48 hours a week
and if i've got pay stubs to do that
you know to verify that um you know a
lender might say well it doesn't say
guaranteed
so yeah you know i want to throw that
one over to eaton because we've had a
lot of you know sort of covid related
policy changes and trying to treat
people that
used to be you know much more employed
and now are dealing with less hours in
2020 and 2021 than maybe they used to or
their
job situations a little more tenuous or
maybe they changed jobs in the last
couple of years
do you think you can comment on how we
manage those hourly part-time employees
from a documentation point of view
yeah of course brendan um and thanks for
uh bringing that up chris because that
is uh
uh a really good question um
so like like brendan said um obviously
on the conventional side there is a lot
more flexibility
you know when it comes to these uh these
hourly employees
um one thing that we have noticed uh
you know about the insurers is what
you've mentioned just now
and that is they tend to be a little bit
more sensitive as to whether the words
you know guaranteed hours are there
um you know they're looking for that you
know solid
solid confirmation that you know weekend
week out it's going to be 40.
um where we have noticed you know the
insurers are able to
be a little bit flexible is if that
hourly income is coming from you know a
bigger employer
right so let's say it's you know like uh
like a walmart
you know or like a costco or like you
know some established
um company that can you know
um come through for the employees when
it comes to providing hours
as opposed to maybe a smaller operation
or a mom-and-pop shop
um you know they're a little bit less
lenient on that
um you know most letters nowadays for
hourly employees won't see guaranteed
from what we see right but what we
what we have noticed is that you know
for the bigger companies it tends not to
be a problem
but for smaller companies it it really
is a coin toss sometimes
so uh i've told the clients they need to
give me at least two
maybe even three months of pay stub
showing that they really are getting 38
to 48 hours a week
you know just to but yourself the
application so
okay i understand yeah i think you know
like
that's what the insurers would would be
comfortable with you know like
at least uh a month or so of of of trend
so i think that's that's a good way to
mitigate and it gives us as the lender
you know at least something to ask for
an escalation yeah
thank you thank you all right
i'm going to talk about some of the
value adds that icici bank delivers
they include things like free title
insurance for purchases and switches
we talked about that 80 rental offset
that's available in the rental worksheet
that's available for you
the ccb being used as income up to 100
in most cases the extended ratios that
we talked about for qualifying borrowers
and we have some favorable treatments of
things like
the heating components where you're
excluding it on
investment properties and you're using a
very reasonable number on
you know owner occupied subject
properties and we talked about
credit and beacons earlier you can also
order your appraisals directly so you
don't have to go through a solidifier
now as you can if you want
but we're not going to make that
requirement we have a list of approved
appraisers on our
portal and you can pick your favorite
one
when it comes to important documentation
that we're going to see sometimes
there's some things we want up front
other times we're going to condition for
a bunch of documents for private
mortgages we have a process
you know we have a need to see some
documents up front
things like the mortgage statement uh
the mortgage charge
for that uh private mortgage holder some
bank statements and some employment
documentation we'll want to see up front
so if you have one of those private
mortgage payout exit strategy files give
me a call before you send it in and i'll
make sure that it's teed up to be
successful right out of the gate if you
have a file that's
going to use a rental worksheet to
substantiate some of the income
we're going to want to see that probably
upfront before we issue a commitment
appraisals for rural properties we don't
we don't do a lot of rural properties
when we say rural
and it's icici you still really need to
be able to see your neighbor across the
street
if it's you know a ranch we probably
aren't going to do that but sometimes
we're going to ask for an appraisal up
front
depending on how far out of town the
property is
if you're doing a down payment from
multiple sources we're probably going to
want to know about that up front as well
what if you can see your neighbor but
your neighbor is a ranch
that's a really good hypothetical
question you send me that file and we'll
talk about it
maybe one of our brokers looks like that
i don't know i'm not just saying
i can i can see the ranch from the
telescope on my front yard yeah
downstream
yeah uh another question for you uh wcb
worksafe long-term disability can you
use that income and can it be bonused up
you know when we're looking at
disability we're always going to have a
clause in the conditions that says it's
guaranteed at
age 65 or it's perpetually conditioned
or
conditionally perpetual so the
short-term disabilities and no but
long-term permanent disability
we're happy to use up to 100 of it
uh wcb i remember seeing a clause in our
underwriting guide i don't think i've
had a file that's used wcv in a while
but
i think there's a discounted amount do
you remember on the wcb if there's a
partial use of it
workers compensation uh personally i've
never i've never seen a wcb
income is that something specific to to
bc
because that's not an acronym i've come
across before
yeah it's a workers compensation
disability through uh
through the provincial insurance short
term oh yeah well
actually i don't think we're gonna get a
lot of success from that because we
don't accept the ontario version of it
um i think our yeah ours is called odsp
yeah um yeah i think it's a similar idea
and like brendan said because it's
generally short-term
um it's not something that we can use to
qualify unfortunately
right unless you have a letter that's a
permanent disability
yeah it's going to come from an insurer
it's going to come from like a pension
fund or something like that then then
yeah we're going to look at that letter
and say that's permanent disability
and that's we're fine with that okay
we haven't talked a lot about business
for self you know i've really framed the
conversation about employees that are
purchasing or refinancing i see ici's
philosophy on business for self income
is if it's a sole proprietorship um we
could typically gross up the
line 150 by 15 percent we're looking for
a two-year average in most cases on that
bfs
there's some exceptions but really when
it's
incorporated bfs we have a philosophy
that
the corporations earning belong to the
corporation and the entrepreneurs
earnings belong to the entrepreneur
so what that means is if you have a
corporation that's bringing in a lot of
revenue
but the the founder or the director is
paying themselves a small salary or
paying themselves small dividends each
year
because we don't have a business for
self stated income program at icici that
file probably isn't going to fit for us
so we're looking to see bfs files that
are incorporated where they're paying
themselves a salary
or they're paying themselves dividends
every year and that's the number we're
going to use to
qualify the file brandon do you guys
offer a heloc would you not offer a
heloc now
okay one more question do you offer a
heloc
different answer this time okay yeah
i will refer you to uh one of our
friendly other lenders that offer heloc
on that subject if you have a file that
has a heloc as part of the
the debt servicing um we are going to
look at
the amount that is owed on that heloc
and not necessarily the full balance
that's available
so keep that in mind too
and that's about it so i will make sure
that
deb if she doesn't have it already has
your brokerage
portal login credentials that's where
you're going to be able to find
our most up-to-date rates we're going to
be able to find our up-to-date
appraisals list
program overviews like you probably want
to know what the rates are i can
i don't think i have a slide for that
but our
insured rates as i mentioned i think
earlier are very competitive you can get
an insured rate right now at 1.69 and a
five year fixed
you get a variable rate of prime minus
one percent so you're looking at you
know
one and a half percent as your out the
door rate for a variable right now
it's a very very good rate so you can
pitch to your rate shoppers that come
through your door
on conventional files our most popular
choice is a three year fixed right now
which is set at 2.94 percent and
paying you about 65 basis points if
you're looking for a
shorter term or a longer term one two
four five years um those are available
too all in the
low to mid three percent range and of
course the longer the term you select
the better it's going to pay you
so five year fixed is going to pay you
100 basis points
whereas a one year fix is only going to
payable 50. so the
three year i i find is again the most
popular based on the fact that it's paid
65 basis points which
is a nice fair compensation for the work
that you're going to do
but it's also a pretty good rate for
your conventional borrowers especially
if they have
you know imperfect credit or they're
going to get a decline from the bank
so we're happy to get them in the door
under three percent on a conventional
file
and that's about it for me i see a few
questions in the chat maybe we can go
through those
uh we got most of those asked during
i see one for previous bankruptcy that's
fine if you have a previous bankruptcy
that's been discharged
um our previous consumer proposal has
been discharged by at least a year
um we're happy with that we don't want
to see bankruptcies that have a
piece of property involved but if they
had some troubles paying off the car
loan or paying back their credit cards
then uh
you know once that's been discharged
we're gonna be able to work with them
and deb was just asking if uh when
the meeting is over if you could give
her a call i think she has a question on
a file yeah absolutely
uh does anyone else have any questions
for either brandon or eaton
we will take that as a no or